highlights from the first semester of
Algebra 2 in two and a half minutes
let's start by looking at parent
functions and we can do Transformations
on these functions we can make vertical
changes by multiplying and adding
numbers to f of x and we can make
horizontal changes by multiplying or
adding numbers to X we can also reflect
over the x-axis or y-axis and now
parabolas parabolas are very good at
modeling things like objects being
thrown in the air there are four common
equations for parabolas and these are
called quadratic equations it can come
in vertex form with an a vertex form
with a 4p intercept form or standard
form and depending on which equation you
use you can find the vertex the axis of
symmetry the focus or the directrix now
we can also find the Y intercept by
setting x equal to zero or the X
intercepts by setting y equal to zero
let's talk more about finding the
x-intercepts so they're typically four
ways to solve a quadratic equation when
it's set equal to zero the square roots
method factoring completing the square
or quadratic formula in some situations
one method is best a lot of times you
have your choice a parabola may have two
one or zero X intercepts in the
situations where there are zero
x-intercepts we still have solutions to
the equation Asians but they're complex
Solutions using I or I squared is equal
to negative one or you could think of it
as I is equal to the square root of
negative one when solving these and a
negative shows up into the square root
you know the solution will be complex
polynomial function all of these are
polynomial functions all of these are
not polynomial functions polynomial
functions have terms with coefficients
and whole number exponents being added
together we can add subtract multiply
and divide polynomials the degree of a
polynomial is the same as the highest
exponent and the number of zeros or
roots or x-intercepts of a polynomial
function is the same as that degree if
we start doing fractional exponents we
call these radical functions whenever
you have a fractional exponent the
denominator is the index of the radical
and the numerator is still the exponent
so the square root of x could be written
as x to the one half the cube root of x
could be x to the one third and the
fifth root of x squared would be x to
the two-fifths up to now we've been
working with X to some exponent what if
we go crazy and put X in the exponent
this is called an exponential function
and this is where exponential growth or
Decay comes from so we can solve for x
in exponential equations too but it
requires an inverse process this is the
reason that we created logarithms the
whole goal of a logarithm is to get the
variable out of the exponent here's a
pretty solid way to think of logarithms
and for practical purposes logarithms
have a lot of properties using these
properties we can expand logarithms we
can condense logarithms we can solve
them in our head but ultimately all this
training for logarithms is meant to
prepare us for the main event anytime we
need to solve an equation where the
variable is in an exponent and this
concludes the highlights from Algebra 2
first semester how exciting